What’s the best way
to stay healthy
in the face of so much
conflicting nutrition information?
Well, ideally, you would
go to the source.
The gold standard;
the peer-reviewed
medical literature.
Read through stacks of
the latest medical journals.
But who’s got
time for that?
I do!
Welcome to the
Nutrition Facts Podcast.
I’m your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
Today we look at the
pros and cons of coffee
for the liver, mind and brain.
And we start by asking
which coffee is healthier:
light roast or dark roast?
For those drinking non-paper-
filtered coffee, like boiled,
French press, or Turkish coffee,
the amount of cholesterol-
raising compounds
in the lightest roast coffee
may be twice as high
compared to using
very dark roast beans.
So, it appears some of the cholesterol-
raising compounds are destroyed by roasting;
so, in this case darker
would be better, or…
you can just use a paper filter
and eliminate 95 percent
of the cholesterol-raising
activity of coffee regardless
of the roast as I’ve described before.
But I did another video showing
dark roasting may also destroy
up to nearly 90 percent of
the chlorogenic acids,
which are the antioxidant,
anti-inflammatory phytonutrients
purported to account for
many of coffee’s benefits.
So, in that case, light
roast would be better.
On the other hand, dark roasting
can wipeout up to 99.8 percent
of pesticides in conventionally
grown coffee,
and more than 90 percent
of a fungal contaminant
called ochratoxin, which is
a potent kidney toxin found
in a wide range of food ingredients
that can get moldy.
But then, what about the polycyclic
aromatic hydrocarbon products
of combustion that are suspected
to be carcinogenic and DNA damaging?
Darker roasts may have up to four
times more than light roasts.
Thus, they advocate controlling
roasting conditions
to cut down on these
combustion compounds.
Just to put things in perspective,
even the darkest roast coffee
might only max out at a fraction of
a nanogram of benzopyrene per cup—
considered to be the most
toxic of these compounds—
whereas a single medium
portion of grilled chicken
could have over 1,000 times more.
Overall, you don’t know
if light versus dark roast
is better until you…
put it to the test.
This study found that dark roast coffee
is more effective than light roast coffee
in reducing body weight.
Folks were randomized to a month
of drinking two cups a day
of light roast coffee
or dark roast coffee,
roasted from the same
batch of green coffee beans.
And in normal weight subjects
it didn’t seem to matter—
no significant weight
changes either month—
but in overweight study subjects,
they ended up about six pounds lighter
drinking dark roast coffee
compared to light roast coffee;
more than a pound a week lost just
drinking a different type of coffee.
What about light versus dark
in relation to blood sugars?
We've known since 2015 that
even a single cup of coffee
can affect the blood sugar response.
What is not known is whether
this increase in blood sugars
is actually clinically meaningful.
After all, coffee consumption does not
seem to increase the risk of diabetes,
and if you compare light roast
coffee to dark roast coffee
right before chugging down
about 20 teaspoons of sugar,
there didn’t appear to be any difference.
Perhaps the take home
message is: light or dark,
maybe we shouldn’t be adding
20 spoonfuls of sugar.
And finally, what about
the effect of different roasts
on heartburn and stomach upset?
We know that “coffee consumption
is sometimes associated
with symptoms of stomach discomfort;”
and so, researchers stuck pH
probes down into people’s stomachs
to measure the amount of stomach acid
generated by different types of coffee.
The way you chart stomach
acid secretion in the stomach
is called a “gastrogram.”
You basically give people
some baking soda,
which starts out alkaline, and
measure the pH in the stomach
to see how long it takes the
body to restore the stomach
back down into an acid bath:
about 15, 20 minutes.
But if you mix that same amount of
baking soda with dark roast coffee,
it takes longer, meaning
the dark roast coffee
is suppressing stomach acid secretion,
since it takes longer
to normalize the pH.
Give people more of a medium
roast coffee, though,
and we see a dramatically
different effect—
an acceleration of stomach
acid secretion,
returning the stomach to acidic
conditions three times faster
than drinking dark roast
coffee, hence the title:
“..[dark roast coffee] is less effective
at stimulating [stomach] acid secretion…
compared to a medium roast [coffee]”,
but you don’t know if that translates
into symptoms—clinical effects—
until you put it to the test.
“The most commonly used
coffee bean roasting process
is referred to as convection or ‘flash’
roasting,” which just takes a few minutes.
“An alternative method
is conduction roasting,”
which roasts at a lower temperature
for a longer time—hours—
and this results in
so-called low acid coffee.
And, supposedly, there are anecdotes
from coffee-sensitive individuals
suggesting that this low-acid coffee
“does not precipitate
or aggravate heartburn.”
When you look up that citation,
though, they just cite data
from the Puroast Coffee company,
makers of low acid coffee.
It should therefore come to no surprise
that it was the same company
that funded the study.
If you go their website, they claim that
“the health benefits associated with drinking
Puroast Low Acid coffee will
become almost immediately obvious
to those who suffer from acid
reflux, heartburn, or indigestion”,
with over 90 percent of customers
surveyed receiving symptom relief;
and so, they decided to put
their money where mouth was.
But before I get to the results,
it’s important to realize that
when they say low acid, they’re
not talking about stomach acid;
they’re talking about roasting
so long that they destroy
more of the chlorogenic
acid within the coffee bean.
You know the antioxidant, polyphenol,
phytonutrient chlorogenic acid...
You know the anti-diabetic, anti-cancer,
anti-inflammatory,
anti-obesity antioxidant...
But hey, if it causes less stomach
discomfort maybe it’s worth it?
Thirty coffee-sensitive
individuals completed
a randomized, double-blind, crossover
study in which the symptoms
of heartburn, regurgitation,
and stomach upset were assessed
following the consumption of the
Puroast brand low acid coffee
versus conventionally roasted
regular Starbucks coffee,
and to the funder’s chagrin,
no benefit whatsoever was found
with the low acid coffee.
Consumption of both coffees
resulted in heartburn, regurgitation,
and stomach upset in most individuals.
So much for that ridiculous
90 percent-of-customers claim.
No significant differences
in the frequency or severity
of heartburn, regurgitation, or
dyspepsia were demonstrated
between the two coffees, either in a
fasting state or after a test meal.
They couldn’t find any way to make
the low acid coffee look better.
So, they had this initial thought
that a difference in coffee acidity
may explain the company’s claims;
however, when put to the test
in a randomized, controlled study,
they found no difference in symptoms,
suggesting the whole coffee
acidity thing doesn’t explain
the sensitivity some people
have, and I think further,
acts as a reminder that we
should never believe claims
made by anyone trying
to sell us something.
In our next story,
we discover new data
that suggests even
paper-filtered coffee
may raise LDL cholesterol.
In a video I did a decade ago—
I explained that the cholesterol-raising
factor in coffee does not pass through
a drip coffee paper filter.
Give people French press coffee,
which is filtered, but without paper,
and their cholesterol swells up
over time starting within just two weeks,
but switch them to paper-filtered coffee,
and their cholesterol comes
right back down.
Same amount of coffee,
but just prepared differently.
The cholesterol-raising factor from
coffee beans has since been identified—
it’s the fatty substances in the oil
within coffee beans.
One reason it took us so long
to figure that out is that it didn’t
raise cholesterol in rats or hamsters,
or even monkeys, but it did
in human beings.
But, it apparently gets stuck
in the paper filter.
This explains why filtered coffee
doesn’t affect cholesterol,
whereas boiled, French press,
or Turkish coffees do.
Espresso as well, which has 20 times
more of the cholesterol-raising
substance cafestol than
paper-filtered drip coffee,
with Turkish and boiled coffee
being the worst,
though instant and percolator coffee
are pretty low, even without
the paper filter.
Note, if you make drip coffee
with one of those metal mesh filters
without the paper, it would presumably
be just as bad as like the French press.
So, the studies in general appeared
to consistently find that it was
this fatty component that was then
filtered out by paper,
but a small number of studies suggested
that filtered coffee may also increase
cholesterol levels, and began to cast
some doubt onto what appeared
to be a fairly clear picture.
So, yeah, the cholesterol-raising
effects brought about
by the consumption
of filtered coffee may not be as strong
as those of the boiled coffee,
but maybe we shouldn’t discard
the possibility that filtered coffee
may also play a small, but important,
role in raising cholesterol.
I knew about this study,
where three cups a day of filtered coffee
raised total cholesterol,
but the rise in LDL “bad” cholesterol
was not statistically significant.
Same with this study, where stopping
filtered coffee reduced total cholesterol,
suggesting perhaps only partial removal,
but no one had ever just measured
the levels of the cholesterol-raising
compounds in the paper filters…
until now.
The results showed that most of the
cholesterol-raising cafestol was retained
by the coffee grounds, rather than
actually getting stuck in the filter itself.
In other words, the principal function
of the paper filter is to not
necessarily to block the compound
itself, but to block any fine particles
that are carrying the compound.
Like, when you make French press coffee,
there’s that fine mesh screen,
but you still notice a little sludge
at the bottom of the cup;
that’s the tiny particles that pass through
and can carry some of the risk.
But, a little cafestol does
get through the filter.
So, yeah, you can cut out more than
90% – switching from French press,
or one of the metal mesh filters,
by using a paper filter.
If you use coffee that starts out
with a high level of
the cafestol compound,
you’re still clearing out about 95%
with the paper, but there may be
enough left to still bump your LDL,
but you don't know until you...
put it to the test.
They started out with
a high cafestol coffee.
After a month of drinking
two cups a day,
their LDL cholesterol
went up significantly,
even though it was paper-filtered.
So, if you have high cholesterol despite
eating a healthy diet, you may want
to try cutting out coffee
and getting retested.
Or, you can try switching to a
lower cafestol coffee.
There’s all sorts of variables,
such as roasting degree or grind size
that may affect cafestol levels.
One can imagine a smaller particle size
would allow for greater extraction.
Roasting appears to destroy some of it;
so, a really dark roast should have less.
But, there’s not much difference between
just light and medium roast.
Indeed, in this study, there was no
significant difference between the
rise in cholesterol after a medium
light roast versus a medium roast.
They both raised bad cholesterol.
Finally today,
we look at the effects of tea
and coffee for artery function.
There are dietary guidelines for food,
but what about for beverages?
A Beverage Guidance Panel was
assembled to provide guidance
on the relative health and nutritional benefits
and risks of various beverage categories.
They ranked them from 1 to 6,
and water ranked #1.
Soda ranked last at #6.
Whole milk was grouped with beer, with a
recommendation for zero ounces a day,
in part out of concern for links
between milk and prostate cancer,
as well as aggressive ovarian
cancer thanks to IGF-1.
#2 on the list, though, after water,
was tea and coffee,
preferably without
creamer or sweetener.
Even without creamer, though, lots of unfiltered
coffee can raise cholesterol levels,
but the cholesterol-raising compounds are
trapped by the paper filter in brewed coffee,
so filtered coffee
is probably better.
About 10 years ago a study was
published on the effects of coffee
on endothelial function -
the function of our arteries.
Within 30 minutes of
drinking a cup of coffee
there is a significant drop in
the ability of our arteries to dilate,
whereas decaf did not seem to
have a significant effect.
This was the first study to demonstrate
an acute unfavorable effect
on arterial function
for caffeinated coffee,
but one cup of decaf didn’t
seem to affect performance.
And two cups of decaf appeared
to have a beneficial effect.
So maybe it’s a battle between
caffeine and antioxidants.
Something in caffeinated coffee appears
to be hurting arterial function,
whereas something in decaf appears to
be helping—maybe the antioxidants.
It’s like the story with red wine.
De-alcoholized red wine significantly
improves arterial function,
so there’s grape components
trying to help,
but the presence of alcohol
counteracts and erases the benefit.
Drinking really high antioxidant coffee,
by preparing it Greek style, for example,
where you actually drink
some of the grounds,
may actually offer
an advantage.
That something in caffeinated coffee
that appears to hurt, though,
may NOT be the caffeine.
In a randomized, double-blind,
placebo-controlled, cross-over study,
researchers found that caffeine
alone—about 2 1/2 cups of coffee worth—
—significantly IMPROVED arterial function in
both people without and with heart disease.
See coffee contains more than a thousand
different components other than caffeine,
many of which are also removed
by the decaffeination process,
so there must be something else in the
coffee bean that’s causing the problem.
In fact, caffeine may even enhance the repair
of the fragile inner lining of our arteries,
by enhancing the migration of
our endothelial progenitor cells,
the stem cells that patch up potholes
in our artery walls, one could say.
But how might we get the
potential benefit of caffeine
without the risky compounds
in caffeinated coffee?
Tea.
Tea consumption enhances
artery function.
Substantial beneficial effects from
both green tea and black tea.
Instead of other components in tea leaves
undermining caffeine’s potential benefits,
they appear to boost the
benefit in healthy individuals,
as well as heart
disease patients,
reversing some of their
arterial dysfunction,
both immediately and
in the long term.
Now all the measurements in
this and the other studies
were done on the brachial artery,
the main artery in the arm,
just because it’s
easier to get to.
What we care about, though,
is blood flow to the heart.
And caffeine appears to impair
blood flow to our heart muscle
during exercise even
in healthy folks,
but especially those
with heart disease.
Thankfully caffeine in tea form
appears to have the opposite effect,
significantly improving
coronary blood flow,
suggesting that tea consumption has a
beneficial effect on coronary circulation,
though the addition of milk may
undermine the protective effects.
We would love it if you could
share with us your stories
about reinventing your health
through evidence-based nutrition.
Go to nutritionfacts.org/testimonials.
We may share it on our social
media to help inspire others.
To see any graphs, charts, graphics,
images, or studies mentioned here,
please go to the Nutrition Facts
Podcast landing page.
There you’ll find all the
detailed information you need –
plus, links to all of the sources
we cite for each of these topics.
For a vital, timely text on the
pathogens that cause pandemics,
order the e-book,
audiobook, or hard copy
of my latest book,
“How to Survive a Pandemic”.
For recipes, check out
my new “How Not to Diet Cookbook”.
It’s beautifully designed
with more than 100 recipes
for delicious and
nutritious meals.
And, of course, all the proceeds
I receive from the sales
of all my books
go to charity.
NutritionFacts.org is a nonprofit,
science-based public service,
where you can sign up
for free daily updates
on the latest in nutrition research
via bite-sized videos and articles.
Everything on the
website is free.
There’s no ads, no
corporate sponsorship,
no kickbacks.
It’s strictly non-commercial.
I’m not selling anything.
I just put it up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to
my grandmother,
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.